[CLICK]
[SQUEAK]
[PAGES RUSTLING]
[MOUSE DOUBLE-CLICKS]
PROFESSOR: So today we'll be
continuing along the theme
of risk stratification.
I'll spend the first half
to 2/3 of today's lecture
continuing where we
left off last week
before the discussion.
I'll talk about how does
one derive the labels
that one uses within a
supervised machine learning
approach.
I'll continue talking
about how one evaluates
risk stratification models.
And then I'll talk about
some of the subtleties that
arise when you
want to use machine
learning for health
care, specifically
for risk stratification.
And I think that's
going to be one
of the most interesting
parts of today's lecture.
In the last third
of today's lecture,
I'll be talking about
how one can rethink
the supervised machine
learning problem,
not to be a
classification problem,
but be something closer
to a regression problem.
And one now thinks about not
will someone, for example,
develop diabetes within one
to three years from now,
but when precisely will
they develop diabetes--
so the time to event.
Then one has to start to
really think very carefully
about the censoring issues
that I alluded to last week.
And so I'll formalize
those notions
in the language of
survival modeling.
And I'll talk about how one
can do maximum likelihood
estimation in that setting, and
how one should do evaluation
in that setting.
So in our lecture
last week, I gave you
this example of risk
stratification for type 2
diabetes.
The goal, just to remind
you, was as follows.
25% of people in
the United States
have undiagnosed
type 2 diabetes.
If we could take
health insurance claims
data that's available
for everyone
who has health
insurance, and use
that to predict who, in the
near-term-- next one to three
years-- is likely to be newly
diagnosed with type 2 diabetes,
then we could use it to
risk-stratify patient
population.
We could use that, then, to
figure out who is most at risk,
do interventions
for those patients,
to try to get them diagnosed
and get them started
on treatment if relevant.
But what I didn't
talk much about
was where did those
labels come from.
How do we know that someone had
a diabetes onset in that window
that I show up there on the top?
So what are the answers?
I mean, all of you should have
read the paper by Razavian.
And then also you should
hopefully have some ideas.
Thoughts?
A hint-- it was in
supplementary material.
How did we define a
positive case in that paper?
Yep.
AUDIENCE: Drugs they were on.
PROFESSOR: Drugs they were on.
OK, yeah, so for example,
metformin, glucose--
sorry, insulin.
AUDIENCE: I think they did
include metformin actually.
PROFESSOR: Metformin
is a tricky case.
Because metformin is often used
for alternative indications.
But there are many
medications, such as insulin,
which are used pretty
exclusively for treating
diabetes.
And so you can look
to see, does a patient
have a record of taking one
of these diabetic medications
in that window that we're
using to define the outcome?
If you see a record
of a medication,
you might conjecture, this
patient probably has diabetes.
But what about it they don't
have any medication listed
in that time window?
What could you conclude then?
Any ideas?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: If you look
at the HBA1C value,
and you know the normal range,
and if you see the [INAUDIBLE]
above like 7.5 or 7.
PROFESSOR: So you're giving
me an alternative approach,
not looking at medications,
but looking at laboratory test
results.
Look at their HBA1C
results, which
measures approximately an
average of three-month glucose
values.
And if that's out of range,
then they're diabetic.
And that's, in
fact, usually used
as a definition of diabetes.
But that didn't answer
my original question.
Why is just looking at diabetic
medications not enough?
AUDIENCE: Some of the
diabetic medications
can be used to treat
other conditions.
PROFESSOR: Sometimes
there's ambiguity
in diabetic medications.
But we've sort of
dealt with that
already by trying to
choose an unambiguous set.
What are other reasons?
AUDIENCE: You're starting
with the medicine at the onset
of diabetes [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Oh, that's a
really interesting point--
not the one I was thinking
about, but I like it--
which is that a patient might
have been diagnosed with type 2
diabetes, but they,
for whatever reason,
in that communication
between provider and patient,
they decided we're not going
to start treatment yet.
So they might not yet be
on treatment for diabetes,
yet the whole health
care system might
be very well aware that
the patient is diabetic,
in which case doing these
interventions for that patient
might be irrelevant.
Yep, another reason?
AUDIENCE: So a lot of
people are just not
diagnosed for diabetes.
So they have it.
So one label means that
they have diabetes,
and the other label is a
combination of people who
have and don't have diabetes.
PROFESSOR: So the
point was, often
you just might not be
diagnosed for diabetes.
That, unfortunately,
is not something
that we're going to
able to solve here.
It is an issue, but we
have no solution for it.
No, rather there's a different
point that I want to get at,
which is that this
data has biases in it.
So even if a patient is
on a diabetes medication,
for whatever reason--
maybe they are paying
cash for those medications.
If they're paying cash
for those medications,
then there's not going to be any
record for the patient taking
those medications in the
health insurance claims.
Because the health insurer
didn't have to pay for it.
But the reason that you gave is
also a very interesting reason.
And both of them are valid.
So for all of these reasons,
just looking at the medications
alone is going to
be insufficient.
And as was just
suggested a moment ago,
looking at other indicators,
like, for example,
does the patient have an
abnormal blood glucose value
or HBA1C value would
also provide information.
So it's non-trivial, right?
And part of what you're going
to be doing in your next problem
set, problem set 2, is going
to be thinking through how
does one actually do this cohort
construction, not just what
is your inclusion/exclusion
criteria,
but also how do you
really derive those labels
from that data set.
Now the traditional answer
to this has two steps to it.
Step 1 is to actually
manually label some patients.
So you take a few
hundred patients,
and you go through their data.
You actually look at
their data, and decide,
is this patient diabetic
or are they not diabetic?
And the reason why you have to
do that is because often what
you might think of is obvious--
like, oh, if they're on diabetes
medication, they're diabetic--
has flaws to it.
And until you really dig
down and look at the data,
you might not recognize that
that criteria has a flaw in it.
So that chart review is
really an essential part
of this process.
Then the second
step is, how do you
generalize to get that
label now for everyone
in your population.
And again, there, there are
usually two different types
of approaches.
The first approach is to
come up with some simple rule
to try to then
extrapolate to everyone.
For example, if they have,
A, diabetes medication,
or an abnormal lab
test result, that
would be an example of a rule.
And then you could then
apply that to everyone.
But even those rules can
be really tricky to derive.
And I'll show you some examples
of that in just a moment.
And as we know,
machine learning is
sometimes good as an alternative
for coming up with a rule.
So there's often now
a second approach
to this being more
and more commonly used
in the literature, which is to
actually use machine learning
itself to derive the labels.
And this is a bit subtle,
because it's machine
learning for machine learning.
So I want to break that
down for one second.
When you're trying to
derive the labels, what
you want to know
is not, at time T,
what's going to happen at
time T plus W and onwards--
that's the original
machine learning task
that we set out to solve--
but rather, given
everything you know
about the patient,
including the future data,
is this patient newly diagnosed
with diabetes in that window
that I show in black there,
between T plus W and onward.
OK?
So for example, this
machine learning problem,
this new machine
learning problem,
could take, as input, lab
test results, and medications,
and a whole bunch of other data.
And you then use the few
examples you labeled in step 1
to try to predict, is
this patient currently
diabetic or not.
You then use that
model to extrapolate
to the whole population.
And now you have
your outcome label.
It might be a little
bit imperfect,
but hopefully it's much
better than what you
could have gotten with a rule.
And then, now
using those outcome
labels, you solve your original
machine learning problem.
Is that clear?
Any questions?
AUDIENCE: I have one.
PROFESSOR: Yep.
AUDIENCE: How do you
evaluate yourself then,
if you have these
labels that were
produced with machine learning,
which are probabilistic?
PROFESSOR: So that's where this
first step is really important.
You've got to get
ground truth somehow.
And of course once you
get that ground truth,
you create a train-and-validate
set of that ground truth.
You run your machine learning
algorithm with the trained one.
You'd look at its
performance metrics
on that validate set for the
label prediction problem.
And that's how you
get confidence in it.
But let's try to break
this down a little bit.
So first of all, what does this
chart review step look like?
Well, if it's an
electronic health record
system, what you often do is you
will pull up Epic, or Cerner,
or whatever the
commercial EHR system is.
And you will actually start
looking at the patient data.
You'll read notes written
by previous doctors
about this patient.
And you'll look at
their blood test results
across time, medications
that they're on.
And from that you
can usually tell
pretty coherent story what's
going on with your patient.
Of course even better-- or
the best way to get data
is to do a prospective study.
So you actually have a
research assistant standing
in the room when a patient
walks into a provider.
And they talk to the
patient, and they take down
really very clear notes
what this patient has,
what they don't have.
But that's usually too
expensive to do prospectively.
So usually what we do is
do this retrospectively.
Now, if you're working with
health insurance claims data,
you usually don't have the
luxury of looking at notes.
And so what, in my group, we
type typically do is we build,
actually, a visualization tool.
And by the way, I'm a
machine learning person.
I don't know anything
about visualization.
Neither do I claim
to be good at it.
But you can't do the machine
learning work unless you really
understand your data.
So we had to build this tool
in order to look at the data,
in order to try to do that
first step of understanding,
did we even characterize
diabetes correctly.
So I'm not going
go deep into it.
By the way, you
can download this.
It's an open source tool.
But ballpark what I'm showing
you here is one patient's data.
I'm showing on
this x-axis, time,
going from April to December.
And on the y-axis, I'm showing
events as they occurred.
So in orange are
diagnosis codes that
were recorded for the patient.
In green are procedure codes.
In blue are laboratory tests.
And if you see, on a
given line, multiple dots
along that same line, it
means that same lab test
was performed multiple times.
And you could click on it to
see what the results were.
And in this way, you could start
to tell a coherent story what's
going on with your patient.
All right, so tools
like this is what
you're going to
need to able to do
that first step from something
like health insurance claims
data.
Now, traditionally,
that first step,
which then leads you to
label some data, and then,
from there, you go and
come up with these rules,
or do a machine learning
algorithm to get the label,
usually that's a
paper in itself.
Of course, not of interest to
the computer science community,
but of extreme interest to
the health care community.
So usually there's a first
paper, academic paper,
which evaluates this process
for deriving the label,
and then there are much later
papers which talk about what
you could do with that label,
such as the machine learning
problem we originally
set out to solve.
So let's look at an example
of one of those rules.
Here is a rule, to derive
from health insurance claims
data whether a patient
has type 2 diabetes.
Now, this isn't quite the same
one that we used in that paper,
but it gets the idea across.
First you look to see, did
the patient have a diagnosis
code for type 1 diabetes.
If the answer is
no, you continue.
If the answer is yes,
you've sort of ruled out.
Because you say, OK, this
patient's abnormal blood test
results are because they
have type 1 diabetes, not
type 2 diabetes.
Type 1 diabetes
usually is what you
can think of as
juvenile diabetes,
is diagnosed much earlier.
And there's a different
mechanism behind it.
Then you look at other things--
OK, is there a
diagnosis code for type
2 diabetes somewhere
in the patient's data?
If so, you go to the
right, and you look to see,
is there a medication,
an Rx, for type
1 diabetes in the data.
If the answer is no, you
continue down this way.
If the answer is
yes, you go this way.
A yes of a type 1
diabetes medication
doesn't alone rule
out the patient.
Because maybe the
same medications
are used for type
1 as for type 2.
So there's some other
things you need to do there.
Right, you can see that this
starts to really quickly become
complicated.
And these manual-based
approaches
end up having pretty
bad positive--
so they're designed
usually to have pretty high
positive predictive value.
But they end up having
pretty bad recall,
in that they don't end up
finding all of the patients.
And that's really why the
machine-learning-based
approaches end up
being very important
for this type of problem.
Now, this is just one example
of what I call a phenotype.
I call this a phenotype.
That's just what the
literature calls it.
It's a phenotype
for type 2 diabetes.
And the word, phenotype,
in this context
is exactly the same
thing as the label.
Yep.
AUDIENCE: What is abnormal mean?
PROFESSOR: For example, if the
HA1C result is 6.5 or higher,
you might say the
patient has diabetes.
AUDIENCE: OK, so this is a
lab result, not a medical--
PROFESSOR: Correct,
yeah, thanks.
Other questions.
AUDIENCE: What's the
phenotype, which part exactly
is the phenotype,
like, the whole thing?
PROFESSOR: The
whole thing, yeah.
So the construction,
where you say--
you follow this
decision tree, and you
get to a conclusion, which
is case, which means,
yes they're type 2 diabetic.
And if ever you don't reach this
point, then the answer is no,
they're not type 2 diabetic.
That's what I mean
by-- so that labeling
is what we're calling the
phenotype of type 2 diabetes.
Now later in the
semester, people
will use the word, phenotype,
to mean something else.
It's an overloaded term.
But this is what it's called
in this context as well.
Now here's an example
of a website--
it's from the PheKB project--
where you will
find tens to close
to 100 of these
phenotypes that have
been arduously created
for a whole range
of different conditions.
OK, so if you go
to this website,
and you click on any
one of these conditions,
like appendicitis,
autism, cataracts,
you'll see a different diagram
of this sort I just showed you.
So this is a real thing.
This is something that the
medical community really
needs to do in order to try
to derive the label that we
can then use in our
machine learning task.
AUDIENCE: I'm just curious,
is the lab value ground truth?
Like if somebody has
diabetes, then they must have
[INAUDIBLE].
It means they have been
diagnosed, and they must have--
PROFESSOR: Well,
so, for example,
you might have an
abnormal glucose
value for a variety of reasons.
One reason is because
you might have
what's called gestational
diabetes, which
is diabetes that's
induced due to pregnancy.
But those patients
typically-- well,
although it's a
predictive factor,
they don't always have
long-term type 2 diabetes.
So even the
laboratory test alone
doesn't tell the whole story.
AUDIENCE: You could be
diagnosed without having
abnormal diabetic?
PROFESSOR: That's
much less common here.
The story will
change in the future,
because there will be a
whole range of new diagnosis
techniques that might use
new modalities, like gene
expression, for example.
But typically, today, the
answer is yes to that.
Yep.
AUDIENCE: So if these
are made by doctors,
does that mean, for
every single disease,
there's one
definitive phenotype?
PROFESSOR: These
are usually made
by health outcomes
researchers, which usually
have clinicians on their team.
But the type of people who
often work on these often
come from the field of
epidemiology, for example.
And so what was
your question again?
AUDIENCE: Is there
just one phenotype
for every single disease?
PROFESSOR: Is
there one phenotype
for every different disease?
In the ideal world, you'd
have at least one phenotype
for every single disease
that could possibly exist.
Now, of course, you
might be interested
in different aspects.
Like you might be
interested in not knowing
just does the
patient have autism,
but where they are on
their autism spectrum.
You might not be
interested in knowing just,
do they have it
now, but you also
might want to know
when did they get it.
So there's a lot of subtleties
that could go into this.
But building these
up is really slow.
And validating them to
make sure that they're
going to work
across multiple data
sets is really challenging, and
usually is a negative result.
And so it's been a
very slow process
to do this manually,
which has led me
and many others to start
thinking about the machine
learning approaches for
how to do it automatically.
AUDIENCE: Just as a
follow-up, is there
any case where there's,
like, five autism phenotypes,
for example, or
multiple competing ones?
PROFESSOR: Yes.
So there are often many
different such rule-based
systems that give you
conflicting results.
Yes, that happens all the time.
AUDIENCE: Can these
rule-based systems
provide an estimate of when
their condition was onset?
PROFESSOR: Right,
so that's getting
at one of the subtleties I just
mentioned-- can these tell you
when the onset happened?
They're not typically
designed to do that,
but one can come up
with one to do it.
And so one way to
try to do that is
you change those rules to have
a time period associate to it.
And then you can imagine
applying those rules
in a sliding window
to the patient data
to see, when is the first
time that it triggers.
And that would be
one way to try to get
a sense of when onset was.
But there's a lot of
subtleties to that, too.
So I'm going to move on now.
I just want to give it some
sense of what that deriving
the labels ends up looking like.
Let's now turn to evaluation.
So a very commonly used
approach in this field
is to compute what's known as
the Receiver-Operator Curve,
or ROC curve.
And what this looks
at is the following.
First of all, this
is well-defined
for a binary
classification problem.
For a binary
classification problem
when you're using a
model that outputs,
let's say, a probability
or some continuous value,
then you could use that
continuous valid prediction.
If you wanted to
make a prediction,
you usually threshold it, right?
So you say, if it's greater than
0.5, it's a prediction of 1.
If it's less than 0.5,
prediction of zero.
But here we might be interested
in not just what minimizes,
let's say, 0-1 loss,
but you might also
be interested in
trading off, let's say,
false positives for
false negatives.
And so you might choose
different thresholds.
And you might want
to quantify how
do those trade-offs look
for different choices
of those thresholds of this
continuous value prediction.
And that's what the ROC
curve will show you.
So as you move along the
threshold, you can compute,
for every single threshold,
what is the true positive rate,
and what is the
false positive rate.
And that gives you a number.
And you try all
possible thresholds,
that gives you a curve.
And then you can compare curves
from different machine learning
algorithms.
For example, here,
I'm showing you,
in the green line, the
predictive model obtained
by using what we're calling the
traditional risk factors, so
something like eight
or 10 different risk
factors for type 2 diabetes
that are very commonly used
in the literature.
Versus in blue, it's
showing you what
you'd get if you just used
a naive L1-regularized
logistic regression model
with no domain knowledge,
just sort of throw in
the bag of features.
And you want to be up there.
You want to be in
that top left corner.
That's the goal here.
So you would like
that blue curve
to be up there, and then
all the way to the right.
Now, one way to try to
quantify in a single number
how useful any one
ROC curve is is
by looking at what's called
the area under the ROC curve.
And mathematically, this is
exactly what you'd expect.
This area is the area
under the ROC curve.
So you could just
integrate the curve,
and you get that number out.
Now, remember, I
told you you want
to be in the upper
left quadrant.
And so the goal
was to get an area
under the ROC curve of a 1.
Now, what would a random
prediction give you?
Any idea?
So if you're to just
flip a coin and guess--
what do you think?
AUDIENCE: 0.5.
PROFESSOR: 0.5?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Well, so I was a
little bit misleading when
I said you just flip a coin.
You got to flip a coin with
sort of different noise rates.
And each one of
those will get you
sort of a different
place along this curve.
And if you look at
the curve that you
get from these
random guesses, it's
going to be the straight
line from 0 to 1.
And as you said, that will
then have an AUC of 0.5.
So 0.5 is going to
be random guessing.
1 is perfect.
And your algorithm is going
to be somewhere in between.
Now, of relevance to the
rest of today's lecture
is going to be an
alternative definition--
alternative way of computing
the area under the ROC curve.
So one way to compute it
is literally as I said.
You create that curve,
and you integrate
to get the area under it.
But one can show
mathematically--
I'm not going to give
you the derivation here,
but you can look
it up on Wikipedia.
One can show mathematically
that an equivalent
way of computing the
area under the ROC curve
is to compute the probability
that an algorithm will
rank a positive-labeled
patient over a negative-labeled
patient.
So mathematically
what I'm talking about
is the following thing.
You're going to sum over
pairs of patients where--
I'm going to call x1 is a
patient with label y1 equals 1.
And x2 is a patient
with label y--
actually, I'll call it--
yeah, with label x2 equals 1.
So these are two
different patients.
I think I'm going to rewrite
it like this-- xi and xj,
just for generality's sake.
So we're going to sum this
up over all choices of i
and j such that yi and
yj have different labels.
So that should say yj equals 0.
And then you're
going to look at--
what you want to happen,
like suppose that you're
using a linear model here.
So your prediction is given
to you by, let's say, w.xj.
What you want is that this
should be smaller than w.xi.
So the j data point,
remember, was the one
that got the 0-th and
the i-th data point
is the one that got the 1 label.
So we want the score of the
data point that should've been 1
to be higher than the score
of the data point which
should've gotten the label 0.
And you just count up-- this
is an indicator function.
You just count up how many of
those were correctly ordered.
And then you're just going to
normalize by the total number
of comparisons that you do.
And it turns out that that
is exactly equal to the area
under the ROC curve.
And it really makes clear
that this is a notion that
really cares about ranking.
Are you getting the ranking
of patients correct?
Are you ranking
the ones who should
have been given 1 higher
than the ones that
should have gotten the label 0.
And importantly,
this whole measure
is actually invariant
to the label imbalance.
So you might have a very
imbalanced data set.
But if you were to
re-sample with now making
it a balanced data set, your
AUC of your predictive model
wouldn't change.
And that's a nice
property to have
when it comes to evaluating
settings where you might have
artificially created
a balanced data set
for computational concerns.
Even though the true setting
is imbalanced, there at least
you know that the
numbers are going to be
the same in both settings.
On the other hand, it also
has lots of disadvantages.
Because often you don't
care about the performance
of the whole entire curve.
Often you care about particular
parts along the curve.
So for example, in
last week's lecture,
I argued that really
what we often care about
is just the positive
predictive value
for a particular threshold.
And we want that to be as high
as possible for as few people
as possible.
Like, find the 100
most risky people,
and look at what
fraction of them
actually developed
type 2 diabetes.
And that setting, what
you're really looking at
is this part of the curve.
And so it turns out
there are generalizations
of area under the curve that
focus on parts of the curve.
And that goes by the
name of partial AUC.
For example, if you just
integrated from 0 to,
let's say, 0.1 of
the curve, then
you could still get a number to
compare two different curves,
but it's focusing on the area
of that curve that's actually
relevant for your
predictive purposes,
for your task at hand.
So that's all I want to
say about receiver-operator
characteristic curves.
Any questions?
Yep.
AUDIENCE: Could you talk more
about what the drawbacks were
of using this.
Does the class imbalance--
is the class imbalance, then,
always a positive effect?
PROFESSOR: So the thing is, when
you want to use this approach,
depending on how you're
using the [INAUDIBLE],,
you might not be
able to tolerate
a 0.8 false positive rate.
So in some sense, what's going
on in this part of the curve
might be completely
irrelevant for your task.
And so one of the algorithms--
so one of these curves--
might look like it's
doing really, really
well over here, and
pretty poorly over here.
But if you're looking at the
full area under the ROC curve,
you won't notice that.
And so that's one
of the big problems.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: And when would you
use this versus precision
recall or--
PROFESSOR: Yeah, so a
lot of the community
is interested in
precision recall curves.
And precision recall
curves, as opposed
to receiver-operator
curves, have the property
that they are not invariant
to class imbalance, which
in many settings is of
interest, because it
will allow you to capture
these types of quantities.
I'm not going to go into
depth about your reasons
for one or the other.
But that's something that
you could read up about,
and I encourage you to
post to Piazza about,
and we have
discussion on Piazza.
So the last evaluation quantity
that I want to talk about
is known as calibration.
And calibration, as
I've defined it here,
has to do with binary
classification problems.
Now, before you dig
into this figure, which
I'll explain in a
moment, let me just
give you the gist of what
I mean by calibration.
Suppose that your model
outputs a probability.
So you do logistic regression.
You get a probability out.
And your model says,
for these 10 patients,
that their likelihood of dying
in the next 48 hours is 0.7.
Suppose that's what
your model output.
If you were on the receiving
end of that result,
so you heard that,
0.7, what should you
expect about those 10 people?
What fraction of
them should actually
die in the next 48 hours?
Everyone could scream out loud.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: So seven of them.
Seven of the 10 you would expect
to die in the next 48 hours
if the probability for all of
them that was output was 0.7.
All right, that's what
I mean by calibration.
So if, on the other
hand, what you
found was that only
one of them died,
then it would be a very weird
number that you're outputting.
And so the reason why this
notion of calibration,
which I'll define formally
in a second, is so important,
is when you're out
putting a probability,
and when you don't really
know how that probability is
going to be used.
If you knew-- if you had
some task loss in mind.
And you knew that
all that mattered
was the actual prediction, 1
or 0, then that would be fine.
But often predictions
in machine learning
are used in a much
more subtle way.
Like for example,
often your doctor
might have more information
than your computer has.
And so often they might
want to take the result
that your computer
predicts, and weigh
that against other evidence.
Or in some settings,
it's not just
weighting about other evidence.
Maybe it's also about
making a decision.
And that decision
might take exertion--
a utility, for example,
a patient preference
for suffering versus getting
a treatment that could
have big, adverse consequences.
And that's something
that Pete is
going to talk about much more
later in the semester, I think,
how to formalize that notion.
But at this point, I just want
to sort of get out the point
that the probabilities
themselves could be important.
And having the
probabilities be meaningful
is something that
one can now quantify.
So how do we quantify it?
Well, one way to
try to quantify it
is to create the
following prompt.
Actually, we'll
call it a histogram.
So on the x-axis is the
predicted probability.
So that's what I meant by p-hat.
On the y-axis is the
true probability.
It's what I mean when I say
the fraction of individuals
with that predicted
probability that actually
got the positive outcome.
That's going to be the y-axis.
So I'll call that
the true probability.
And what we would like
to see is that this
is a line, a straight line,
meaning these two should always
be equal.
And in the example
I gave, remember
I said that there
were a bunch of people
with 0.7 probability
predicted, but for whom
only one out of them actually
got the positive end.
So that would have been
something like over here.
Whereas you would have
expected it to be over there.
So you might ask, how
do I create such a plot
from finite data?
Well, a common way to do
so is to bin your data.
So you'll create intervals.
So this bin is the
bin from 0 to 0.1.
This bin is the bin from
0.1 to 0.2, and so on.
And then you'll look to see,
OK, how many people for whom
the predicted probability
was between 0 and 0.1
actually died?
And you'll get a number out.
And now here's where
I can go to this plot.
That's exactly what
I'm showing you here.
So for now, ignore the
bar charts and the bottom,
and just look at the line.
So let's focus on
just the green line.
Here I'm showing you
several different models.
For now, just focus
on the green line.
So the green line, by the way,
notice it looks pretty good.
It's almost a straight line.
So how did I compute it?
Well, first of all,
notice the number of ticks
are 1, 2, 3, 4,
5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
OK, so there are 10
points along this line.
And each of those corresponds
to one of these bins.
So the first point
is the 0 to 0.1 bin.
The second point is the
0.1 to 0.2 bin, and so on.
So that's how it computed this.
The next thing you
notice is that I
have confidence intervals.
And the reason I compute
these confidence intervals
is because sometimes
you just might not
have that much data
in one of these bins.
So for example, suppose
your algorithm almost never
said that someone has a
predictive probability of 0.99.
Then until you
get a ton of data,
you're not going to know what
fraction of those individuals
actually went on to
develop the event.
And you should be looking
at sort of the confidence
interval of this line,
which should take that
into consideration.
And a different way to try to
understand that notion, now
looking at the
numbers, is what I'm
showing you in the bar
charts in the bottom.
On the bar charts,
I'm showing you
the number of individuals or
the fraction of individuals
who actually got that
predicted probability.
So now let's start
comparing the lines.
So the blue line shown
here is a machine
learning algorithm which
is predicting infection
in the emergency rooms.
It's a slightly different
problem than the diabetes one
we looked at earlier.
And it's using a bag of words
model from clinical text.
The red line is using
just chief complaint.
So it's using one piece
of structured data
that you get at one
point of time in the ER.
So it's using very
little information.
And you can see that both models
are somewhat well calibrated.
But the intervals--
the confidence
intervals of both the
red and the purple lines
gets really big towards the end.
And if you look at
these bar charts,
it explains why,
because the models
that use less information end
up being much more risk-averse.
So they will never predict
a very high probability.
They will always sort of
stay in this lower regime.
And that's why we have very
big confidence intervals there.
OK, so that's all I want
to say about evaluation.
And I won't take any
questions on this right
now, because I
really want to get
on to the rest of the lecture.
But again, if you have any
questions, post to Piazza,
and I'm happy to discuss
them with you offline.
So, in summary, we've
talked about how
to reduce risk stratification
to binary classification.
I've told you how to
derive the labels.
I've given you one example
of machine learning algorithm
you can use, and I talked to
you about how to evaluate it.
What could possibly go wrong?
So let's look at some examples.
And these are a small number of
examples of what could possibly
go wrong.
There are many more.
So here's some data.
I'm showing you--
for the same problem
we looked at before,
diabetes onset, I'm
showing you the prevalence of
type 2 diabetes as recorded by,
let's say, diagnosis
codes across time.
All right, so over here is 1980.
Over here is 2012.
Look at that.
It is not a flat line.
Now, what does that mean?
Does that mean that the
population is eating much more
unhealthy from 1980 to
2012, and so more people
are becoming diabetic?
That would be one
plausible answer.
Another plausible explanation
is that something has changed.
So in fact I'm showing you
with these blue lines, well,
in fact, there was a change
in the diagnostic criteria
for diabetes.
And so now the patient
population actually
didn't change much
between, let's say,
this time point at
that time point.
But what really led
it to this big uptick,
according to one theory, is
because the diagnostic criteria
changed.
So who we're calling
diabetic has changed.
Because diseases are,
at the end of the day,
a human-made concept, you know,
what do we call some disease.
And so the data is
changing, as you see here.
Let me show you another example.
Oh, by the way, so the
consequence of that is that
automatically-derived labels--
for example, if you use
one of those phenotyping
algorithms I showed you
earlier, the rules--
what the label is
derived for over here
might be very different
from the label that's
derived from over
here, particularly
if it's using data such
as diagnosis codes that
have changed in
meaning over the years.
So that's one consequence.
There'll be other consequences
I'll tell you about later.
Here's another example.
And by the way, this notion
is called non-stationarity,
that the data is
changing across time.
It's not stationary.
Here's another example.
On the x-axis again
I'm showing you time.
Here each column is a
month, from 2005 to 2014.
And on the y-axis, for every
sort of row of this table,
I'm showing you a
laboratory test.
And here we're not looking at
the results of the lab test,
we're only looking
at what fraction
of-- at how many lab
tests of that type
were performed at
this point in time.
And now you might expect
that, broadly speaking,
the number of glucose tests,
the number of white blood cell
count tests, the number of
neutrophil tests and so on
might be pretty constant
across time, on average,
because you're averaging
over lots of people.
But indeed what you see
here is that, in fact,
there is a huge amount
of non-stationarity.
Which tests are
ordered dramatically
changes across time.
So for example you see
this one line over here,
where it's all blue, meaning
no one is ordering the test,
until this point in time,
when people start using it.
What could that be?
Any ideas?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: So the test was used
less, or really, in this case,
not used at all.
And then suddenly it was used.
Why might that happen?
In the back.
AUDIENCE: A new test.
PROFESSOR: A new test, right,
because technology changes.
Suddenly we come up with a
new diagnostic test, a new lab
test.
And we can start using it,
where it didn't exist before.
So obviously there was
no data on it before.
What's another reason why it
might have suddenly showed up?
Yep.
AUDIENCE: It could be like
annual check-ups become
mandatory, or that it's part of
the test admission at hospital.
Like, it's an additional test.
PROFESSOR: I'll stick
with your first example.
Maybe that test
becomes mandatory.
OK, so maybe there's
a clinical guideline
that is created at this
point in time, right there.
And health insurers
decide we're going
to reimburse for this test
at this point in time.
And the test might've
been really expensive.
So no one would have
done it beforehand.
And now that the health
insurance companies
are going to pay for it,
now people start doing it.
So it might have
existed beforehand.
But if no one would pay for
it, no one would use it.
What's another reason why you
might see something like this,
or maybe even a gap like this?
Notice, here in
the middle, there's
this huge gap in the middle.
What might have explained that?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Hold on.
Yep, over here.
AUDIENCE: Maybe your
patient population
is mostly of a certain age,
and coverage for something
changes once your age
crosses a threshold.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, so
one explanation--
I think it's not plausible
in this data set,
but it is plausible
for some data sets--
is that maybe your
patients at time 0
were all of exactly
the same age.
So maybe there's some
amount of alignment.
And suddenly, at this
point in time, let's say,
women only get, let's say,
their annual mammography
once they turn a certain age.
And so that might be one reason
why you would see nothing
until one point in time.
And maybe that would
change across time as well.
Maybe they'll stop getting it
at some point after menopause.
That's not true, but let's say.
So that's one explanation.
In this case, it
doesn't make sense,
because the patient
population is very mixed.
So you could think about it as
being roughly at steady state.
So they're not-- you'll have
patients of all ages here.
What's another reason?
Someone raised their
hand over here.
Yep.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I was
just going to say,
maybe the EMR shut
down for awhile,
and so they were only
doing stuff on paper,
and they only were able
to record 4 things.
PROFESSOR: Ding
ding ding ding ding.
Yes, that's right.
So maybe the EMR shut down.
Or in this case,
we had data issues.
So this data was
acquired somehow.
For example, maybe
it was required
through a contract
with something
like Webquest or LabCorp.
And maybe, during that
four-month interval,
there was contract negotiation.
And so suddenly we
couldn't get the
Data for that time period.
Or maybe our databases
crashed, and we suddenly
lost all the data
for that time period.
This happens, and this
happens all the time,
and not just the
health care industry,
but other industries as well.
And as a result of those
systemic-type changes,
your data is also going to be
non-stationary across time.
So now we've seen three or
four different explanations
for why this happens.
And the reality is really
a mixture of all of these.
And just as in the previous--
so in the previous example,
notice how what really
changed here is that
the derived labels might
change meaning across time.
Now the significance
of the features
used in the machine
learning models
would really change across time.
And that's one of the
consequences of this,
particular if you're driving
features from lab test values.
Here's one last example.
Again, on the x-axis
here, I have time.
On the y-axis here, I'm
showing the number of times
that you observed some
diagnosis code of some kind.
This cyan line is ICD-9 codes.
And this red line
are ICD-10 codes.
You might remember that Pete
mentioned in an earlier lecture
that there was a big shift from
ICD-9 coding to ICD-10 coding
at some point.
When was that time?
It was precisely this time.
And so if you think about the
feature vector that you would
derive for your machine
learning problem,
you would have one feature
for all ICD-9 codes, and one--
a whole set of features
for all ICD-10 codes.
And those ICD-9-based
features are
going to be-- they're going
to be used quite a bit
in this time period.
And then suddenly they're
going to be completely
sparse in this time period.
And ICD-10 features
start to become used.
And you could imagine that
if you did machine learning
using just ICD-9
data, and then you
tried to apply your model
at this point in time,
it's going to do horribly,
because it's expecting features
that it no longer has access to.
And this happens all the time.
And in fact, what
I'm describing here
is actually a major problem for
the whole health care industry.
For the next five
years, everyone
is going to grapple
with this problem,
because they want to use their
historical data for machine
learning, but their
historical data
is very different from
their recent data.
So now, in the face of all of
this non-stationarity that I
just described, did we do
anything wrong in the diabetes
risk stratification problem
that I told you about earlier?
Thoughts.
That was my paper, by the way.
Did I make an error?
Thoughts.
Don't be afraid.
I'm often wrong.
I'm just asking
specifically about the way
I evaluated the models.
Yep.
AUDIENCE: This wasn't
an error, but one thing,
like if I was a doctor
I would like to see
is the sensitivity to--
like, the inclusion
criteria if I
remove the HBA1C for instance.
Like most people, they have
compared to having either Rx
or [INAUDIBLE] then
kind of evaluating the--
PROFESSOR: So understanding
the robustness
to changing the data a
bit is something that
would be of a lot of interest.
I agree.
But that's not
immediately suggested
by the non-stationarity results.
Not something that's suggested
by non-stationarity results.
Our TA in the front
row has an idea.
Yeah, let's hear it.
AUDIENCE: The train
and test distributions
were drawn from the
same-- or the train
and tests were drawn from
the same distribution.
PROFESSOR: So in the way that
we did our evaluation there,
we said, OK, we're going to set
it up such that on January 1,
2009, we're predicting
what's going to happen
in the following three years.
And we segmented our
patient population
into train, validate, and
test, but at all times,
using that same setup, January
1 2009, as the prediction time.
Now, we learned this
model, and it's now 2018.
We want to apply
this model today.
And I computed an area
under the ROC curve.
I computed positive
predictive values
using that retrospective data.
And I handed those
off to my partners.
And they might hope that those
numbers are reflective of what
their models would do today.
But because of these issues
I just told you about--
for example, that
the number of people
who have type 2 diabetes,
and even the definition of it
has changed.
Because of the fact that
the laboratory-- ignore
this part over here.
That's just a fluke.
But the fact, because
of the laboratory
tests that were
available during training
might be different from the
ones that are available now,
and because of the fact that
we have only ICD-10 data now,
and not ICD-9, for
all of those reasons,
our predictive
performance is going
to be really horrible
now, Particularly
because of this last issue
of not having ICD-9s.
Our predictive model is
going to work horribly
now if it was trained on
data from 2008 or 2009.
And so we would have
never ever even recognized
that if we used the validation
set up that we had done there.
So I wrote that paper when
I was young and naive.
[AUDIENCE CHUCKLING]
I'm a little bit
more gray-haired now.
And so in our more recent
work-- for example,
this is a paper which
we're working on right now,
done by a master's student
of mine, Helen Zhou,
and is looking at predicting
antibiotic resistance,
now we're a little bit smarter
about over evaluation setup.
And we decided to set it up
a little bit differently.
So what I'm showing
you now is the way
that we chose,
trained, validated
and test for our population.
So we segmented our data.
So the x-axis here is time,
and the y-axis here are people.
So you can think of each person
as being a different row.
And you can imagine that we
randomly sorted the rows.
What we did is we segmented our
data into these four quadrants.
The first two quadrants, we
used for train and validate.
Notice, by the way, that
we have different people
in the training set as we
do in the validate set.
That's important for
another quantity which
I'll talk about in a minute.
So we used this data
for train and validate.
And that's, again,
very similar to the way
we did it in the diabetes paper.
But now, for testing,
we use this future data.
So we used data
from 2014 to 2016.
And one can imagine two
different quadrants.
You might be
interested in knowing,
for the same patients for
whom you made predictions
on during training, how
would your predictions do
for those same people at
test time in the future data.
And that's assuming that
what we're predicting
is something that's much
more myopic in nature.
In this case it was
predicting, are they
going to be resistant
to some antibiotic?
But you can also look at it
for a completely different set
of patients, for
patients who are not
used during training at all.
And suppose that this 2
bucket isn't used at all,
for those patients,
how do we do, again,
using the future data for that.
And the advantage
of this setup is
that it can really help you
assess non-stationarity.
So if your model
really took advantage
of features that were
available in 2007, 2008, 2009,
but weren't available
in 2014, you
would see a big drop
in your performance.
Looking at the
drop in performance
from your validate set
in this time period,
to your test set from
that time period,
that drop in performance
will be uniquely attributed
to the non-stationarity.
So it's a good way
to diagnose it.
Yep.
AUDIENCE: Just
some clarification
on non-stationarity-- is it the
fact that certain data is just
lost altogether,
or is it the fact
that it's just
encoded differently,
and so then it's difficult
to get that mapping correct?
PROFESSOR: Both.
Both of these happen.
So I have a big
research program now
which is asking not just how--
so this is how you can
evaluate and recognize
there's a problem.
But of course there's a really
interesting research question,
which is, how can you make
use of the non-stationarity.
Right, so for example,
you had ICD-9/ICD-10 data.
You don't want to just
throw away the ICD-9 data.
Is there a way to use it?
So the naive answer, which is
what the community is largely
using today, is come
up with a mapping.
Come up with a manual
mapping from ICD-9 to ICD-10
so that you can sort of
manually transform your data
into this new format
such that the models you
learn from this older time
is useful in the future time.
That's the boring
and simple answer.
But I think we could
do much better.
For example, we can learn new
representations of the data.
We can learn that
mapping directly
in order to optimize
for your sort of most
recent performance.
And there's a whole bunch more
that we can talk about later.
Yep.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
non-stationary change,
this will [INAUDIBLE]
does not ensure robustness
to the future.
PROFESSOR: Correct.
So this allows you to detect
that a non-stationarity has
happened.
And it allows you to say
that your model is going
to generalize to 2014-2016.
But of course, that doesn't
mean that your model's going
to generalize to 2016-2018.
And so how do you do that?
How do you have
confidence in that?
Well, that's a really
interesting research question.
We don't have good
answers to that today.
From a practical perspective,
the best I can offer you today
is, build in these checks
and balances all the time.
So continuously sort
of evaluate how you're
doing on the most recent data.
And if you see big
changes, throw a red flag.
Build more checks and balances
into your deployment process.
If you see a bunch of
patients who are getting
predicted probabilities
of 1, and in the past,
you'd never predicted
probability 1,
that might tell you something.
Then much later in the semester,
we'll talk about robust machine
learning approaches,
for example,
approaches that have
been designed to be
robust against adversaries.
And those type of
approaches as well
will allow you to be much more
robust to particular types
of data set shift, of
which non-stationarity
is one example.
But it's a big,
open research field.
Yep.
AUDIENCE: So just to make sure I
have the understanding correct,
theoretically, if you
could map everything
from the old data set to the new
data set, like the encodings,
would it still be
OK, like the results
you get on the future data set?
PROFESSOR: If you could
do a perfect mapping,
and it's one to one, and the
distributions of those things
also didn't change, then yeah.
Really what you need to assess
is, is there data set shift?
Is your training
distribution, after mapping,
the same as your
testing distribution?
If the answer is
yes, you're all good.
If you're not,
you're in trouble.
Yep.
AUDIENCE: What seems to be the
test set of traits set here?
Or what [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: So 1 is using
data only from 2007-2013,
3 is using data
only from 2014-2016.
AUDIENCE: But in the case,
like, the output we care about
happened in, like,
2007-2013, then
that observation would be
not-- it wouldn't be useful.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, so for
the diabetes problem,
there's also just
inclusion/exclusion criteria
that you have to deal with.
For what I'm showing you here,
I'm talking about a setting
where you might be making
multiple predictions
for patients across time.
So it's a much more
myopic prediction task.
But one could come
up with an analogy
to this for the
diabetes setting.
Like, for example, just hold out
half of the patients at random.
And then for your training
set, use data up to 2009,
and evaluate on data
only up to 2013.
And for your test set, pretend
as if it was January 1, 2013,
and look at
performance up to 2017.
And so that would be--
you're changing your prediction
time to use more recent data.
So the next subtlety is--
it's a name that I put on to it.
This isn't a standard name.
This is what I'm calling
intervention-tainted outcomes.
And so the example here came
from your reading for today.
The reading was this paper
on intelligible models
for health care predicting
pneumonia risk in hospital
30-day admissions from KDD 2015.
So in that paper,
they give an example--
it's a very old example--
of trying to use
a predictive model
to understand a patient's
risk of mortality
when they come
into the hospital.
And what they learned-- and
they used a rule-based learning
algorithm-- and
what they discovered
was a rule that said if
the patient has asthma,
then they have
low risk of dying.
So these are all patients
who have pneumonia.
So a patient who comes in
with pneumonia and asthma
has a lower risk of
dying than a patient who
comes in with pneumonia and does
not have a history of asthma.
OK, that's what this rule says.
And this paper argued
that there's something
wrong with that learned model.
Any of you remember
what that was?
Someone who hasn't
talked today, please.
Yeah, in the back.
AUDIENCE: It was that
those with asthma
had more aggressive treatment.
So that means that they had
a higher chance of survival.
PROFESSOR: Patients with asthma
had more aggressive treatment.
In particular, they
might have been
admitted to the
intensive care unit
for more careful vigilance.
And as a result, they
had better outcomes.
Yes, that's exactly right.
So the real story behind this
is that risk stratification,
as we talked about
the last couple weeks,
it's used to drive
interventions.
And those interventions, if
they happened in the past data,
would change the outcomes.
So in this case,
you might imagine
using the learned
predictive model to say,
a new patient comes in,
this new patient has asthma,
and so we're going to
say they're low risk.
And if we took a naive action
based on that prediction,
we might say, OK,
let's send them home.
They're at low risk of dying.
But if we did that, we
could be killing people.
Because the reason
why they were low
risk is because they had those
interventions in the past.
So here's what's going
on in that picture.
You have your
data, X. And you're
trying to make a prediction at
some point in time, let's say,
emergency department triage.
You want to predict
some outcome Y,
let's say, whether the patient
dies at some defined point
in the future.
Now, the challenge is that, as
stated in the machine learning
tasks that you saw there,
all you had access to
was X and Y, the covariance of
the features and the outcome.
And so you're
predicting Y from X,
but you're marginalizing
over everything
that happens in between, in
this case, the treatment.
So the good outcomes,
people surviving,
might have been due to
what's going on in between.
But what's going on
in between is not
even observed in the
data necessarily.
So how do we address
this problem?
Well, the first thing I
want you to think about
is, can we even recognize
that this is a problem?
And that's where
that article really
suggests that using an
unintelligible model, a model
that you can introspect and
try to understand a little bit,
is actually really important
for even recognizing
that weird things are happening.
And this is a
topic which we will
talk about in a lecture towards
the end of the semester in much
more--
Jack will talk about
algorithms for interpreting
machine learning models.
So that's important.
You've got to recognize
what's going on.
But what do you do about it?
So here are some hacks.
Hack number 1--
modify the model.
This is the solution that is
proposed in the paper you read.
They said, OK, if it's a
simple rule-based prediction
that the learning
algorithm outputs to you,
you could see the rule
that doesn't make sense,
you could use your
clinical insight
to recognize it
doesn't make sense.
You might even be able to
explain why it happened.
And then you just
remove that rule.
So you manually modify the model
to push it towards something
that's more sensible.
All right, so that's
what was suggested.
And I think it's nonsense.
I don't think that's ever
going to work in today's world.
In today's world of
high-dimensional models,
there's always going to be
surrogates which are somehow
picked up by a
learning algorithm
that you will not
even recognize.
And it will be really hard
to modify it in the way
that you want.
Maybe it's impossible using the
simple approach, by the way.
Another interesting
research question--
how do you actually
make this work
in a high-dimensional setting?
But for now, let's say we
don't know how to do it
in a high-dimensional setting.
So what are your other choices?
Hack number 2 is to redefine
the outcome altogether,
to change what
you're predicting.
So for example, if you
go back to this picture,
and instead of
trying to predict Y,
death, if you could try to find
some surrogate for the thing
you care about, which
is pre-treatment,
and you predict
that thing instead,
then you'll be back in business.
And so, for example, in one
of the optional readings for--
or actually I think in the
second required reading
for today's class,
it was a paper
about risk revocation
for sepsis, which
is often caused by infection.
And what they show
in that article
is that there are laboratory
test results, such as lactate,
and there are others,
which can give you
a hint that this patient
might be on a path
to clinical deterioration.
And that test might precede
the interventions to try
to take care of that condition.
And so if you instead
change your outcome
to be predicting that
surrogate, then you're
getting around this problem
that I just pointed out.
Now, a third hack is from
one of the optional readings
from today's lecture,
this paper by Suchi
Saria and her students, from
Science Translational Medicine
2015.
It's a really
well-written paper.
I highly recommend reading it.
In that paper, they suggest
formalizing the problem
as one of censoring,
which is what
we'll be talking about for
the very last third of today's
lecture.
In particular, what
they say is suppose
you see that a patient is
treated for the condition.
Let's say they're
treated for sepsis.
Then if the patient is
treated for that condition,
then we don't know what would
have happened to them had they
not been treated.
So we don't observe the outcome,
death given no treatment.
And so we're going to treat
it as an unknown outcome.
And for patients who were
not treated, but ended up
dying due to sepsis, then
they're not censored.
And what I'll show you in
the later part of the class
is how to learn
from censored data.
So this is another
formalization which
tries to address this
problem that we pointed out.
Now, I call these hacks
because, really, I
think what we should be
doing is formalizing it using
the language of causality.
Once you do this
introspection and you
realize that there is
treatment, in fact,
you should be rethinking
about the problem as one
of now having three
quantities of interest.
There's the patient, everything
you know about them at triage.
That's the X-variable
I showed you before.
There's the outcome,
let's say, Y.
And then there's
that everything that
happened in between, in
particular the interventions
that happened in between.
We'll call that
T, for treatment.
And the question
that one would like
to ask in order to figure
out how to optimally care
for the patient is one of,
will admission to the ICU,
which is the intervention
that we're considering here,
will that lower the likelihood
of death for the patient?
And now when I say lower,
I don't mean correlation,
I mean causation.
Will it actually lower the
patient's risk of dying?
I think we need to hit
these questions on the head
with actually thinking
about causality to try
to formalize this properly.
And if you do that,
this will be a solution
which will generalize to the
high-dimensional settings
that we care about
in machine learning.
And this will be a topic that
we'll talk really in-depth
after spring break.
But I wanted to give you this
as one motivation for why
it's so important-- there
are many other reasons--
to really think about it
from a causal perspective.
OK, so subtlety number 3--
there's been a ton of hype in
the media about deep learning
and health care.
A lot of it is very
well warranted.
For example, the
advances we're seeing
in areas ranging from
radiology and pathology
to interpretation of
EKGs are all really
being transformed by
deep learning algorithms.
But the problems
I've been telling you
about for the last
couple of weeks,
of doing risk stratification on
electronic health record data,
such as taxed notes,
such as lab test
results and vital signs,
diagnosis codes, that's
a different story.
And in fact, if you look
closely at all of the papers,
all the papers that
have been published
in the last few years
that have been trying
to apply the gauntlet of
deep learning algorithms
at those problems, in fact,
the gains are very small.
And so what I'm showing you
here is just one example
of such a paper.
This is a paper that received
a lot of media attention.
It's a Google paper
called "Scalable
and Accurate Deep Learning with
Electronic Health Records."
And if you go across
the United States,
if you go
internationally, you talk
to chief medical
information officers,
they're all going to be
telling you about this paper.
They've all read it,
they've all heard about it,
and they all want to use it.
But what is this actually doing?
What's going on
behind the scenes?
Well, this paper
uses the same sorts
of data we've been
talking about.
It takes vitals, notes,
orders, medications,
thinks about it as a
timeline, summarizes it, then
uses a recurrent neural network.
It also uses attentional
architectures.
And there's some pretty
smart people on this paper--
you know, Greg
Corrado, Jeff Dean,
are all co-authors
of this paper.
They know what they're doing.
All right, so they use
these algorithms to predict
a number of downstream
problems-- readmission risk,
for example, 30-day
readmission, like
you read about in your
readings for this week.
And they see they get
pretty good predictions.
But if you go to the
supplementary material, which
is a bit hard to find, but
here's the link for all of you,
and I'll post it to my slides.
And if you look at
the very last figure
in that supplementary
material, you'll
see something interesting.
So here are those
three different tasks
that they studied--
inpatient mortality
prediction, 30-day readmission,
length-of-stay prediction.
The first line each
of these buckets
is what your deep
learning algorithm does.
Over here, they have
two different hospitals.
I think it might
have been University
of Chicago and Stanford.
And they're showing the area
under the ROC curve, which
we've talked about,
performance for each
of these tasks for
their best models.
And in the parentheses, they
give confidence intervals--
let's say something like 95%
confidence intervals-- for area
under the ROC curve.
Now, the second
line that you see
is called full-feature
enhanced baseline.
It's using the
same data, but it's
using something very close
to the feature represetnation
that you saw in the
paper by Narges Razavian,
so that paper on
diabetes prediction
that I told you about and
we've been criticizing.
So it's using that
L1-regularized logistic
regression with a
smart set of features.
And what you see across
all three settings
is that the results are not
physically significantly
different.
So let's look at the first
one, hospital A, deep learning,
0.95 AUC.
This L1-regularized
logistic regression, 0.93.
30-day readmission,
0.77, 0.75, 0.86, 0.85.
And the confidence intervals
are all overlapping.
So what's going on?
So I think what you're
seeing here, first of all,
is a recognition by the machine
learning community that--
in this case, a late recognition
that simpler approaches
tend to work well with
this type of data.
I don't think this was the
first thing that they tried.
They tried probably the deep
learning algorithms first.
Second, we're all
grasping at this,
and we all want to come up
with these better algorithms,
but so far we're
not doing that well.
And I'll tell you more
about that in just a second.
But before I finish
with the slide,
I want to give you a punch line
I think is really important.
You might come home
from this and say,
you know what, it's
not that much better,
but it's a little bit better--
0.95 to 0.93.
Suppose it was tight
confidence intervals,
there might be a few
patients whose lives
you could save with that.
But because all the issues I've
told you about up until now,
of non-stationary, for
example, those gains disappear.
In many cases, they even
reverse when you actually
go to deploy these models
because of that data set shift
for non-stationarity.
It so happens that
the simpler models
tend to generalize better
when your data changes on you.
And this is nicely
explored in this paper
from Kenneth Jung and Nigam
Shah in Journal of Biomedical
Informatics, 2015.
So this is something that
I want you to think about.
Now let's try to answer why.
Well, the areas where
we've been seeing
recurrent neural networks
doing really well--
in, for example,
speech recognition,
natural language processing,
are areas where, often--
for example, you're
predicting what
is the next word in
a sequence of words,
the previous few words
are pretty predictive.
Like, what is the next
[PAUSES] that I'm going to say?
What is it?
AUDIENCE: Word.
PROFESSOR: Word,
right, and you knew
that, right, because it was
pretty obvious to predict that.
And so the models that
are good at predicting
for that type of
data, it doesn't
mean that they should
be good for predicting
for a different type
of sequential data.
Sequential data
which, by the way,
lives in many
different time scales.
Patients who are hospitalized,
you get tons of data for them
at a time, and then
you might go months
without any data on them.
Data with lots of missing data.
Data with multivariate
observations
at each point in time,
not just a single word
at that point in time.
All right, so it's
a different setting.
And we shouldn't expect that
the same architectures that
have been developed
for other problems
will generalize immediately
to these problems.
Now, I do conjecture
that there are
lots of nonlinear
attractions where
deep neural networks
could be very
powerful at predicting for.
But I think they're subtle.
And I don't think that we
have enough data currently
to deal with the fact
that the data is messy
and that the non-linear
interactions are subtle.
We just can't find
them right now.
But this shouldn't mean that
we're not going to find them
a few years from now.
I think this deservedly is
a very interesting research
direction to work on.
And a final reason
to point out is
that the features that are
going into these types of models
are actually really
cleverly-chosen features.
A laboratory test result,
like looking at your A1C--
what is A1C?
So it's something that
had been developed
over decades and decades of
research, where you recognize
that looking at a
particular protein
is actually informative as
something about a patient's
health.
So the features that we're
using that go into these models
were designed--
first, they were designed
for humans to look at.
And second, they were
designed to really help you
with decision-making, or
largely independent features
from other information that
you have about a patient.
And all of those
are reasons, really,
I think why we're
observing these subtleties.
OK, so for the last
10 minutes of class--
I'm going to have
to hold questions,
because I want to get
through all the material.
But please post them to Piazza.
For the last 10
minutes of class,
I want to change
gears a little bit,
and talk about
survival modeling.
So often we want want to
talk about predicting time
to some event.
So this red dot here--
sorry, this black line here
is what I mean by an event.
That event might be, for
example, a patient dying.
It might mean a married
couple getting divorced.
It might mean the day that
what you graduate from MIT.
And the red dot here
denotes censored events.
So for whatever
reason, we don't have
data on this patient, patient
S3, after time step 4.
They were censored.
So we do know that
the event didn't
occur prior to time step 4.
But we don't know
if and when it's
going to occur
after time step 4,
because we have
missing data there.
OK, so this is what I mean
by right-censored data.
So you might ask, why not
just use classification--
like binary classification--
in this setting?
And that's exactly
what we did earlier.
We thought about formalizing
the diabetes risk stratification
problem as looking to see
what happens years 1 to 3
after the time of prediction.
That was with a gap of one year.
And there a couple
of reasons why
that's perhaps not what
you really wanted to do.
First, you have less data
to use during training.
Because you've suddenly
excluded patients for whom--
or to differently--
if you have patients
for whom they were censored
during that time window,
you're throwing them out.
So you have fewer
data points there.
That was part of our
inclusion/exclusion criteria.
Also, when you go to
deploy these models,
your model might say,
yes, this patient
is going to develop type 2
diabetes between one and three
years from now.
But in fact what happened is
they develop type 2 diabetes
3.1 years from now.
So your model would
count this as a negative.
Or it would be a false positive.
The prediction would
be a false positive.
But in reality, your model
wasn't actually that bad.
We did pretty well.
We didn't quite get
the right range,
but they did get
diagnosed diabetes right
outside that time window.
And so your measures
of performance
are going to be pessimistic.
You might be doing
better than you thought.
Now, you can try to
address these two
challenges in many ways.
You can imagine a multi-task
learning framework
where you try to predict
what's going to happen one
to two years from
now, what's going
to happen two to three years
from now, three to four,
and so on.
Each of those are different
binary classification models.
You might try to tie
together the parameters
of those models via a
multi-task learning formulation.
And that will get you closer
to what you care about.
But what I'll tell you about
in the last five minutes
is a much more elegant approach
to trying to deal with that.
And it's akin to regression.
So that leads to
my second point--
why not just treat this
as a regression problem?
Predict time to event.
You have some continuous
valued outcome,
the time until
diagnosis diabetes.
Just try to minimize
mean squared--
minimize your
squared error trying
to predict that
continuous value.
Well, the first
challenge to think about
is, remember where that
mean squared error loss
function came from.
It came from thinking
about your data
as coming from a
Gaussian distribution.
And if you do maximum likelihood
estimation of this Gaussian
distribution, it
turns out to look
like minimizing a squared loss.
So it's making a lot of
assumptions about the outcome.
For one, it's making
the assumption
that outcome could be
negative or positive.
A Gaussian distribution
doesn't have to be positive.
But here we know that T
is always non-negative.
In addition, there
might be long tails.
We might not know exactly
when the patient's
going to develop
diabetes, but we
know it's not going to be now.
It's going to be at some
point in the far future.
And that may also look
very non-Gaussian.
So typical regression approaches
aren't quite what you want.
But there's another
really important problem,
which is that if you naively
remove those censored points--
like, what do you do for the
individuals where you never
observe the time--
where the never get diabetes,
because they were censored?
Well, if you just remove those
from your learning algorithm,
then you're biasing
your results.
So for example, if you
think about the average age
of diabetes onset, if you only
look at people who actually
were observed to
get diabetes, it's
going to be much closer to now.
Because obviously the
people who were censored
are people who got it much
later from the censoring time.
So that's another
serious problem.
So the way they we're
trying to formalize this
mathematically is as follows.
Now we should think about
having data which has,
again, features x, outcome--
what we usually call Y for
the outcome in regression,
but here I'll call
it capital T, because
of the time to the event.
And now we have an
additional variable--
so it's no longer a
two-point, now it's a triple--
b.
And b is going to be a binary
variable, which is saying,
was this individual
censored-- was the time, t,
denoting a censoring
event, or was it denoting
the actual event happening?
So it's distinguishing
between the red and the black.
So black is b equals 0.
Red is b equals 1.
OK, so now we can talk
about learning a density,
P of t, which I'll
also call f of t,
which is the probability
of death at time t.
And associated with
any density, of course,
is the cumulative
density function,
which is the integral from 0
to any point of the density.
Here we'll actually look
at 1 minus the CDF, what's
called the survival function.
So it's looking at probability
of T, actual time of the event,
being larger than some
quantity, little t.
And that's, of course,
just the integral
of the density from
little t to infinity.
All right, so this is
the survival function.
It's of a lot of interest.
You want to know,
is the patient going
to be diagnosed with diabetes
two or more years from now.
So pictorially, what
you're interested in
is something like this.
You want to estimate these
conditional distributions.
So I call it
conditional because you
want to condition on the
covariant to individual x.
So what I'm showing
you, this black line,
is your density, little f of t.
And this white area
here, the integral
from little t to infinity,
meaning all this white area,
is capital S of t.
It's the probability of
surviving longer than time
little t.
OK, so the first thing
you might do is say,
we get these data,
these tuples, and we
want to try to estimate
that function, little
f, the probability of
death at some time.
Or, equivalently, you
might want to estimate
the survival time, capital S
of t, which is the CDF version.
And these two are related to
another just by some calculus.
So a method called the
Kaplan-Meier estimator
is a non-parametric method
for estimating that survival
probability, capital S of t.
So this is the probability
that an individual lives
more than some time period.
So first I'll explain
to you this plot, then
I'll tell you how to compute it.
So the x-axis of
this plot is time.
The y-axis is this survival
property, capital S of t.
It's the probability
that an individual lives
more than this amount of time.
I think this x-axis is in days,
so 500, 1,000, 1,500, 2,000.
This figure, by the way, was
created by one of my students
who's studying a multiple
myeloma data set.
So you could then ask, well,
under what covariants do you
want to compute this survival?
So here, this method
I'll tell you about,
is very good for when you
don't have any features.
So all you want
to do is estimate
that density by itself.
And of course you
could apply a method
for multiple populations.
So what I'm showing
you here is applying it
for two different populations.
Suppose there's just a
single binary feature.
And we're going to apply
it to the x equals 0
and to x equals 1.
That gets you two
different curves out.
But here the estimator is going
to work independently for each
of the two populations.
So what you see here
on this red line
is for the x equals
0 population.
We see that, at time 0, everyone
is alive, as you would expect.
And at time 1,000,
roughly 60% individuals
are still alive for time 1,000.
And that sort of stays constant.
Now you see that, for
the other subgroup,
the x equals 1 subgroup, again,
time step 0, as you would
expect, everyone is alive.
But they survive much longer.
At time step 1,000, over
75% of them are still alive.
And of course of interest here
is also confidence balance.
I'm not going to tell
you how can you do that,
but it's in some of
the optional readings.
And by the way, there are
more optional readings given
on the bottom of these slides.
And so you see that there is
a statistically significant
difference between x
equals 1 and x equals 0.
These people seem
to be surviving
longer than these people.
And you get that
immediately from this curve.
So how do we compute that?
Well, we take those
observed times,
those capital Ts, and here
I'm going to call them just y.
I'm going to sort them.
So these are sorted times.
And I don't care whether they
were censored or not censored.
So y is just all of the times
for all of the patients,
whether they are
censored or not.
dK I want you think about as 1.
It's the number of events
that occurred at that time.
So if everyone had a unique
time of censoring or death,
then dK is always 1.
K is indexing one
of these things.
n of K is the number
of individuals
alive and uncensored
by the K-th time point.
Then what this estimator
says is that S of t--
so the estimator at
any point in time--
is given to you by
the product over K
such that y of K is
less than or equal to t.
So it's going over the
observed times up to little t,
of 1 minus the ratio of 1 over--
so I'm thinking about dK as 1--
1 over the number of people
who are alive and uncensored
by that time.
And that has a very
intuitive definition.
And one can prove that
this estimator gives you
a consistent estimator
of the number of people
who are alive--
sorry, the number of survival
probability at any one
point in time for censored data.
And that's critical.
This works for censored data.
So I'm past time today.
So I'll finish the last few
slides on Tuesday's lecture.
So that's all for today.
Thanks.